<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>lgbt | Germano Bortolotto</title>
    <link>/category/lgbt/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/lgbt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>lgbt</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>lgbt</title>
      <link>/category/lgbt/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Turing</title>
      <link>/2020/06/28/alan-turing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2020/06/28/alan-turing/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Today, June 28, is internationally known as Pride Day. This date was chosen as a reference to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stonewall_riots&#34;&gt;Stonewall Inn riots&lt;/a&gt;, an episode remembered as a milestone in gay activism. Since that day, much progress has been done towards acceptance and inclusion of LGBTQIA+ people in many places around the world. In this post I want to highlight some contributions made by these people that allowed to world to become what it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my academic and professional life, few names were more cited than that of Alan Turing, the British mathematician known as “the father of modern computing”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born in June 23, 1912, Turing developed some thoughts on the similarities between a brain and a computer, establishing the idea of the brain as a “computing machine”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One concept that is becoming mainstream in the era of Artificial Intelligente (AI) is that of a “thinking machine”. In his 1950 paper, &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/mind/article/LIX/236/433/986238&#34;&gt;“Computing machinery and intelligence”&lt;/a&gt;, Turing proposes that if a computer can provide answers in a way indistinguishable from how a human would perform in natural language conversation, than one could argue the this computes shows a kind of intelligent behavior. In his paper he uses the Imitation Game as starting point to his arguments. Interestingly, the movie &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2084970/&#34;&gt;“The Imitation game”&lt;/a&gt; (2014), an historical drama based on Turing’s life, barely mentions this idea, which is much better exploited in the movie &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0470752/&#34;&gt;“Ex-Machina”&lt;/a&gt; released the following year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides his work on computational science, Turing is also credited for having decoded Enigma’s criptography. Enigma was a a machine used by the Nazis during the Second World War do send coded messages. Once the code was broken, the Allies could anticipate Axis’ moves and act accordingly. This episode is considered one of the war’s turning points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, all his contributions were not enough to save his life. Turing was homosexual, and on 1952 he was prosecuted for “gross indecency”. He had two options: 1. prison; 2. chemical castration. He chose the latter. He was found dead on 1954, victim cyanide poisoning. However, there are some divergences whether it was suicide or accidental poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took almot 60 years to his condenation to be revisited. In 2013, Queen Elizabeth II granted Turing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-25495315&#34;&gt;a posthumous pardon&lt;/a&gt;. It is said that his face will be printed on the £50 note as a recognition for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2019/jul/15/alan-turing-father-of-modern-computing-50-pound-note&#34;&gt;his lifetime works&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Turing’s life and influence in the past 50 years can be taken as an example of the presence and importance of LGBTQIA+ people in the world. Science and culture would not be so advanced or diverse or powerful if not by their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although much as been done in the past years to ensure basic human rights, there is still so much to fight for. Let’s take this day as a celebration of our conquests and a reminder of the lives, sufferings and contributions of the ones that came before. May the Alan Turing’s of today and the future be able to live as they want, be who they are, and contribute to humanity’s growth, no matter their desires and aptitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stonewall_riots&#34;&gt;Stonewall Riots - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turing, Alan (1950), &lt;strong&gt;Computing Machinery and Intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;, Mind, LIX (236): 433–460. &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/mind/article/LIX/236/433/986238&#34;&gt;(link)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2084970/&#34;&gt;The Imitation Game (IMDb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0470752/&#34;&gt;Ex-Machina (IMDb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-25495315&#34;&gt;Royal pardon for codebreaker Alan Turing - BBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2019/jul/15/alan-turing-father-of-modern-computing-50-pound-note&#34;&gt;Turing’s face on the pound note - The Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brazilian LGBT complaints in the past decade</title>
      <link>/2020/06/21/lgbt-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2020/06/21/lgbt-app/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I finally decided to start writing on this website. It was something I wanted for a long time, but always delayed for multiple reasons. The start of the Coronavirus pandemic didn’t help at all… :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to write every week about different subjects. Most of the posts will probably be some tutorials on Python, R, data science and software development as those are the things that keep me busy during the week. However, I might also write about human rights, education and research topics on neuroscience and physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this first post I will present a small app I have been developing in the past few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of this year I looked for data and information involving crimes against LGBT people in Brazil. It is said that we have one of the highest crime rates in the world&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#References&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but I wanted to see the raw data and maybe try to have some insights when studying time series and correlated events on this subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to contact some people from &lt;a href=&#34;https://grupogaydabahia.com.br/&#34;&gt;Grupo Gay da Bahia&lt;/a&gt; but I have never received an answer. I talked to some friends and learned that crimes against LGBT people are rarely registered in official documents in a regular manner. I ended up rummaging the federal government website, notably the “Ministry of Family and Human Rights” but found only their promises of providing updated and open access data on human rights in Brazil. In a page that is no longer accessible, it is said that strategies to be adopted for the opening, support, monitoring and promotion of their database would be produced with deadline for August 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I contacted them on February asking for an update on this issue (the deadline was past for about six months), but after two months of waiting they only said that “all necessary information, schedules and databases to be used will soon be published”. In other words: “we have been working for almost a year and still don’t have anything planned”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, during my time clicking around the Ministry’s website I found that at least SOME information is public. The Brazilian government provides a help line (called &lt;strong&gt;“Disque Denúncia”&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;“Disque Direitos Humanos”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#References&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) so people can call and denounce domestic abuse, child and elderly maltreatment etc. Among the several profiles available, one can see calls coming from LGBT people. There is data from 2011 to 2019 (only partially, as this year’s data covers only until June).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I downloaded all data concerning LGBT people through &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.br/mdh/pt-br/acesso-a-informacao/ouvidoria/balanco-disque-100&#34;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;. The data tables are actually very complete, but all data is just the case counts in multiple categories (sex, age, location…). Because of this I was not able to get any insights from it, but I decided to organize it to make it easier for people to look at some trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to do that, I developed a very simple &lt;strong&gt;Shiny&lt;/strong&gt; application in &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;. You can see the result &lt;a href=&#34;https://gerbortolotto.shinyapps.io/denuncialgbt/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (Portuguese only). Data is separated in tabs representing different complainant profiles. You can see how the cases increases or decreases for different Brazilian states in the past eight years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align:center;&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gerbortolotto.shinyapps.io/denuncialgbt/&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://gbortolotto.github.io/img/denuncia_ex.png&#34; alt=&#34;no css&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I could update this application as new data was released. However, the Brazilian government changed how this information would be released. Their last report sum up the cases in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.br/mdh/pt-br/acesso-a-informacao/ouvidoria/Relatorio_Disque_100_2019_.pdf&#34;&gt;a pdf file&lt;/a&gt; and one can’t access the raw data as I did. If the government decides to releases open data, I will develop a new app and try to provide some kind of easily accessible platform. Until then and without new data I think this app will be just a snapshot of complaints made by LGBT people by middle 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the data used in the development os this app can be found on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gbortolotto/lgbtapp&#34;&gt;Github page&lt;/a&gt; (the code needs some cleaning…) and only exists thanks to projects like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shinyapps.io/&#34;&gt;Shinyapps.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S.: I intend to write in English in this website, but I will probably translate the posts about this app as it concerns primarily the Brazilian LGBT population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT_rights_in_Brazil#Anti-LGBT_violence&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT_rights_in_Brazil#Anti-LGBT_violence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.br/mdh/pt-br/acesso-a-informacao/ouvidoria/balanco-disque-100&#34;&gt;https://www.gov.br/mdh/pt-br/acesso-a-informacao/ouvidoria/balanco-disque-100&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
